## Luis Guillermo Natera Orozco

## Data Analyst

natera@hey.com luisnatera.com +36-30-846-91-65

Motivated, interdisciplinarity team-work oriented, and responsible Data Analyst with significant experience working in urban mobility and data analysis. Highly educated, finishing a Ph.D. in Network Science from the Central European University, where I developed new data analysis methods for the analysis of large-scale urban mobility network data, along with the designing of new algorithms for the quantification of urban liveability and connectivity improvement for bicycle infrastructure networks.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Central European University**

Ph.D. Researcher

01/08/2018 - Present

## **Multimodal Fingerprint of Urban Transportation Networks**

skills

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. Network Science, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary. 2021 (expected)

Dissertation: Multilayer network analysis of sustainable, multimodal urban transport networks

Advisor: Federico Battiston

Co-Advisor: Michael Szell (ITU Copenhagen)

M.A. Communication of Science and Culture, ITESO, Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2015

Dissertation: La construcción de comunidades en red sobre conocimiento urbano en el marco del

crecimiento urbano: Los blogs de espacio público

Advisor: Eduardo Quijano

Committee: Rossana Reguillo, Francisco Morfín

B.Arch. Architecture, ITESO, Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2010

#### **ACADEMIC AFFILIATIONS**

2021 – Research fellow, Agglomeration and Social Networks Research Lab, ELKH Centre for Economic and Regional Studies, Budapest, Hungarian.

2020 – Research affiliate, Observatorio de Ciudades, ITESM, Zapopan, Mexico.

- 2017 Ph.D. Candidate, Department of Network and Data Science, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary.
- 2016–17 Executive Coordinator Signa\_Lab, Department of Sociocultural Studies, ITESO, Tlaquepaque. Mexico
- Visiting Student, Center for Civic Media, Media Lab, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA. USA
- 2008 Visiting Student, Universidad de Valparaíso, Valparaíso, Chile

### RESEARCH AND TEACHING INTERESTS

Network science

Urban planning and mobility

Big data for social good

Data science and data visualization

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles**

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez, G., Szell, M. "Data-driven strategies for optimal bicycle network growth" *Royal Society Open Science*, 2020. 7: 201130. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.201130
- Natera Orozco, L.G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez, G., Szell, M. "Extracting the multimodal fingerprint of urban transportation networks" *Transport Findings*, 2020. https://doi.org/10.32866/001c.13171

## **Journal Article Manuscripts under Peer Review**

Natera Orozco, L. G., Alessandretti, L., Szell, M., Battiston, F. "Multimodal transportation and mobility in urban networks" Under review at *Transportation* 

### **Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings**

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Deritei, D., Vancso, A., Vasarhelyi, O. "Quantifying life quality as walkability on urban networks" In: Cherifi H., Gaito S., Mendes J., Moro E., Rocha L. (eds) Complex Networks and Their Applications VIII. COMPLEX NETWORKS 2019. Studies in Computational Intelligence, 2019, pp. 905–918.
- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Comunicación, ciudad e internet: flujos de información urbana en entornos digitales" VI Seminatio Internacional de Investigación en Urbanismo. Bogota, Colombia.

## **Peer-Reviewed Book Chapters**

- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Un cambio de la comunicación gubernamental y política. De los medios de comunicación a las redes sociales." *Informe Anual Q Medios 2018*, edited by Bernal, G. Jalisco, Mexico: ITESO.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Reguillo, R. "Comunicación y cambio social: participación política e internet en Jalisco" *Enciclopedia Jaliscience de la Comunicación.*, edited by Orozco, G., Reguillo, R. Jalisco, Mexico: Universidad de Guadalajara.

#### **Reviews and Other Articles**

Natera Orozco, L. G., (as Signa\_Lab) "Battle of the hashtags: Mapping the online conversation surrounding Mexico's gas price" *Global Voices*.

## **Manuscripts in Preparation and Development**

Tupikina, L., Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F. "A comparative analysis of station and dockless bike share systems."

## **INVITED TALKS**

- 2021 Bauhaus-Universität Weimar, Germany.
- 2021 URBANUM. Budapest, Hungary.
- 2021 Graph data science. Manning Publications. Online.
- Science, Technology and Innovation Council. Hidalgo, Mexico.
- Neo Urban Networks Workshop. Paris, France.
- 2020 PIP Ciudad Futuro. Guadalajara, Mexico.
- 2019 Data Science MeetUp. Timisoara, Romania.
- FabLab, West University of Timisoara, Timisoara, Romania.
- 2019 4D Cities, Multi-Actor Systems Department, TU Delft. Delft, Netherlands.
- 2019 Mobile and Social Computing Lab, Fondazione Bruno Kessler. Trento, Italy.
- 2019 ANET-Talks, ANET Lab, Hungarian Academy of Science. Budapest, Hungary.
- 2018 Signa\_Lab, ITESO. Tlaquepaque, Mexico.
- 2015 Encuentro de Urbanismo Alternativo, Centro Cultural de España en México. Mexico City, Mexico.
- 2015 II Simposio de ciudades y territorios incluyentes "Derecho a la Ciudad", Universidad Autónoma de Yucatán. Merida, Mexico.

#### **CONFERENCE ACTIVITY**

#### **Conference Presentations**

Presenting author italicized, if other.

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Deritei, D., Vancso, A., Vasarhelyi, O. "Quantifying life quality as walkability on urban networks" VIII Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications. Lisbon, Portugal. December 12-14.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez González, G., and Szell, M. "Multiplex urban fingerprints for bicycle infrastructure planning" Cycling Research Board Meeting. Delft, Netherlands. October 31-1 November.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez González, G., and Szell, M. "Multiplex urban fingerprints for bicycle infrastructure planning" 2019 NetSci. Burlington, Vermont. May 27-31.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F., Szell, M. "Characterizing cities from their multiplex infrastructure patterns" SICC Workshop ComplexCity@PoliTo. Turin, Italy.
- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Quiosco Libre, reading network in the public space" Future of Places. Stockholm, Sweden.

#### **Posters**

- Natera, L. "Budapest. Multilayer urban network" State of the Map. Milan, Italy.
- Natera, L., Ábrego, V. "The evolution of twitter during the US elections" Data Stories. Budapest, Hungary.

#### **GRANTS, AND AWARDS**

#### **Awards**

- 2020 Award for Advanced Doctoral Students. Central European University
- 2019 Best lighting talk award. International Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications.

#### **Grants and Fellowships**

- 2020, 21 Write-up grant. Central European University
- 2019 Registration grant. International Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications
- 2019 Ph.D. conference travel grant. CEU Budapest Foundation
- 2019 Registration grant. NetSci
- 2018, 19 Travel grant. Department of Network and Data Science, Central European University
- 2017–20 Doctoral grant. Central European University.
- 2015 Academic Stay at MIT. Mexican National Council of Science and Technology
- 2013 Master Studies Grant. Mexican National Council of Science and Technology

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

### **European Consortium for Political Research**

Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Summer Virtual Methods School 2021
 Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Winter Virtual Methods School 2021
 Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Summer Virtual Methods School 2020

## **Central European University**

2020	Teaching Assistant, Scientific Pytl	non
------	-------------------------------------	-----

2019 Teaching Assistant, Statistical Methods in Network Science

#### **ITESO**

2019	Network Science (Summer 2019) Invited lecturer, co-taught with Diego Arredondo (ITESO)
2017	Network Science (Summer 2017) Co-taught with Emma Towlson (Northeastern University), Sean P. Cornelius (Northeastern University), and Ricardo Zavala (ITESO)
2015-17	Communication, Culture and Society (Spring 2016, 2017)
2015-16	Social Systems Theory (Fall 2015, 2016)

### **RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

2015–17 Researcher, Anillo Primavera.
Principal Investigator: Sandra Valdes.

2016 Researcher, Online harassment of journalists and activists in Mexico, Jigsaw (formerly Google Ideas) and Global Voices.

Principal Investigator: Ellery Biddle.

2012 Researcher, Public Transportation in Guadalajara. Principal Investigator: Mario Silva.

## **ACADEMIC VISITS**

2015 Center for Civic Media, MIT Media Lab, Boston, USA, Jan - Jun

2012 Universidad de Valparaíso, Valparíso, Chile.

#### SERVICE

#### **Journal Peer Review**

Scientific Data

## **Service to Department**

Ph.D. program representative, Central European University, DNDS, 2019-20 Co-organizer Data Stories visualization exhibition, Central European University, DNDS, 2018-19

## **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

Network Science Society
Python Software Foundation
SICC Italian Society for Chaos and Complexity

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2020-	Latin American Capital, Chief Data Scientist. Guadalajara, Mexico
2020-21	PIP Ciudad Futuro (collaboration with Google.org), Data Scientist Consultant. Guadalajara, Mexico.
2019-20	Latin American Capital, Senior Data Scientist Consultant. Guadalajara, Mexico
2019	Maven7US, Urban Data Scientist. Budapest, Hungary
2015-17	Mesura, Networks and Data Specialist. Guadalajara, Mexico
2014	Socialinks, Networks Consultant. Guadalajara, Mexico
2014	Institute for Mobility and Transportation of the State of Jalisco, Mobility Analyst. Zapopan, Mexico
2010-14	Colectivo Triciclo, Co-Founder / CEO. Guadalajara, Mexico

#### **SKILLS AND METHODS**

## **Statistical and Computational Methods**

Network science methods

Programming, data wrangling and visualization: Python

Web: Django, HTML/Javascript, Wordpress, Jekyll

Network visualization: Gephi, Cytoscape, Matplotlib + NetworkX

Version control: Git + {GitHub, GitLab, BitBucket}

Other: LTEX, Adobe CS, CAD, QGIS, Blender

## Languages

Spanish Native

English Professional proficiency

# Updated August 2021